Okay so today's דף daf is ק"יג Kuf Yud Gimmel and we
pick up at the bottom of ק"יב עמוד ב Kuf Yud Beis
Amud Beis and we are
thank you yeah we're talking about a
cat ג' דברים Gimmel Devarim and
about six lines down. The larger theme of why we've sort of
digressed again is because the משנה Mishna has
mentioned even an
עני ani who's parts from the תמחוי tamchuy needs to have ארבע
כוסות Arba Kosot so the גמרא Gemara traced that to רבי עקיבא'ס
Rabbi Akiva's statement about that a person should rather make their שבת
Shabbos like a weekday in terms of don't spend any extra money
on it rather than having to become dependent on other people and
that was one of the things he told his son he commanded
his son like one of these ethical wills and that led to
a series of things that people are commanding others particularly and also
in the context of
sort of these ethical charges. So we also have the story about
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai in the prison where he didn't want to teach him straight
תורה Torah so he taught him these types of issues. So in
that context we continue now on ק"יב עמוד ב Kuf Yud Beis
Amud Beis six lines down in the wide line beginning of the
line ג' דברים צוה רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי את רבי. Gimmel devarim
tziva Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi es Rabbi. Three things רבי ישמעאל ברבי
יוסי Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yosi commanded רבי. Rabbi. אל תעש מום בעצמך
Al taas mum b'atzmecha
don't make a wound in yourself which basically means don't do behavior
that'll be injurious to yourself not just physical we'll see in a
minute. מאי היא Mai hi well what does that mean? לא תהוי
לך דינא בהדי תלתא. Lo tehavei lach dina bahadi tlata. Don't get
into business dealings or into an argument with three people. Why? Because
you're asking for trouble דחד הוי בעל דינך
ותרי סהדי. d'chad havei baal dincha v'trei sahedi. One of them will
bring a case against you in court and he'll use his other
two pals to be witnesses against you. So you don't want to
get up three against one because that can be asking for trouble.
ואל תעמוד על המקח בשעת שאין לך דמים. V'al taamod al hamekach
b'shaat she'ein lecha damim. Do not look over merchandise if you don't
have any money to spend for it. There's a whole real that's
more like a sort of general ethical charge. There's גמרא Gemara in
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia that discusses the biblical prohibition of well not
גניבת דעת gneivat daat of אונאת דברים onaat devarim
that your actions or words cause people anguish and that you bring
the expectations here of the seller that you're really interested in buying
and then you're not really and you are not going to be
buying.
The רשב"ם Rashbam says you'll degrade the merchandise that part I missed.
Where's he say? בשעת שאין לך דמים לקנות
המקח ונמצא מפסידו חינם. B'shaat she'ein lecha damim liknos hamekach v'nimtza mafsido
chinam.
No
I think it means you're מפסידו mafsido the seller מאחר שאתה מהפך
בו. meachar sheata mehapech bo.
Right. Not degrade the merchandise. You're מפסידו mafsido מאחר שייקחנה
אחר מאחר שאתה
meachar
sheyikachena
acher meachar sheata
oh no no no I didn't understand that it meant that it
was handled. I thought he
meant that the seller is not spending time with other people because
he's spending time with you or somebody sees you looking at it
and putting it down and therefore the other person assumes that there's
something wrong with it. I didn't understand it like just physical use
and degrading but it's more like your presence and your actions lead
to a loss for the owner I believe that.
ואם אתה מהפך בו V'im ata mehapech bo so certain thinks you're
getting it forget about you're putting it down.
Right so it's one of that. Anyway I think that's more the
context. Anyway let's keep on going. Okay אשתך
טבלה Ishtecha tavela if your wife has gone to the מקוה mikvah
אל תזדקק לה לילה ראשונה al tizdakek lah lila rishona which is
totally shocking. Don't have sex the first night. I mean we understand
there's a general understanding that the first night back from the מקוה
mikvah is considered to be like a מצוה mitzvah to have sex
that night. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's never explicit about that the reasons
the פוסקים poskim based that on but anyway here it says דווקא
davka don't have sex the first night. What's that based on? אמר
רב ובנידה דאורייתא. Amar Rav u'beniddah d'Oraita. We're not talking about nowadays.
We're not talking about nowadays that women wait extra clean days after
they stop bleeding. We're talking about a biblical נידה niddah where she
goes to the מקוה mikvah seven days after the onset of bleeding.
It could have been she could have been bleeding the whole seven
days but there's no clean days. It's just seven days after the
onset of bleeding. That's the problem. הואיל והוחזק מעיין פתוח Hoil v'huchzak
maayan patuach because then if she's been bleeding if she's only been
bleeding started bleeding seven days ago her literally the well is still
open. She might still have not finished completely her flow she has
not even though it have been seven days but she hasn't done
clean days like we do or days without blood specifically as we
do nowadays. ודילמא משכא זיבא V'dilma mashcha ziva and maybe therefore there
will still be
some bleeding even afterwards and it'll wind up that you'll be having
that the man will be having sex with his wife when she
is if not a נידה niddah a זבה. zavah. So therefore don't
give it a little extra time. Question.
Yes. So when then was what we
practice whatever get to מסכת נידה Masechet Niddah in מסכת נידה Masechet
Niddah a year ago. What are you asking?
Okay no but what the other is it says לילה ראשונה lila
rishona which implies the second night okay should just say when she
stops then. No.
No, obviously you assume she stopped. I mean most women stop before
seven days anyway. It just means give it like a little buffer
zone, check, make sure that there's, you know, doesn't mean that women
bleed for seven days. But they could. שלושה דברים ציווה רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה את רבי. Shlosha devarim tziva Rabbi Yossi bar Rabbi Yehuda
et Rabbi. Three things Rabbi Yossi bar Rabbi Yehuda commanded Rabbi. Interesting
all these people commanding Rabbi, if you also think about it Rabbi
here is the נשיא nasi and everybody else is commanding him to
do things but okay maybe he was collecting opinion you know he
was collecting sort of like an early פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot or
something I don't know he was collecting you know ethical wills ethical
charges. אל תצא יחידי בלילה. Al tetzei yechidi balayla. We already said
this in the משנה. Mishna. Don't go right don't go out alone
at night now we're back to שדים. shedim. ואל תעמוד בפני הנר
ערום. Ve'al ta'amod bifnei haner arom. Don't stand naked in front of
a candle. Okay you maybe because you think other people will see
you but we'll see the גמרא Gemara will have other types of
health concerns. ואל תיכנס למרחץ חדש. Ve'al tikanes lemerchatz chadash. Now we're
getting real practical. Don't go into a brand new bathhouse שמא תיפחת
shema tipachet
because you're afraid the floor will break below you and basically the
way it is you would stand in a steam room and underneath
they'd have like you know big
hot coals and and water put on it and the steam would
come up and you're standing on a floor wooden floor directly above
that. So if it's brand new and hasn't been tested yet maybe
the floor will break through and you'll fall into the hot coals.
Okay very practical advice. I'm sure you could use it metaphorically for
some other purposes. עד כמה? Ad kama? How long should you wait
before going into a new bathhouse? אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי עד
שנים עשר חודש. Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi ad shneim asar chodesh.
Twelve months. So some people aren't obviously listening to this advice. Alright
anyway. ואל תעמוד בפני הנר ערום. Ve'al ta'amod bifnei haner arom.
Now we go back to explain the other things. Don't stand naked
in front of the candlelight. דתניא detanya as it's taught in a
ברייתא. braita. העומד בפני הנר ערום הוה נכפה. Ha'omed bifnei haner arom
havei nichpeh. If you stand naked in front of candlelight you will
become a you'll get epilepsy.
Who knows what that's based on presumably some שד shed influence or
something I don't know. והמשמש מיטתו לאור הנר. Vehamishmesh mitato le'or haner.
And somebody who has sex in front by candlelight the גמרא Gemara
is about issues about having sex you know what you know in
daylight and so on. So somebody who has sex in candlelight הויין
לו בנים נכפין havayan lo banim nichpin will have children who have
who have epilepsy. I don't know exactly what that's about but maybe
I could suspect here that the issue is is that if sex
is is supposed to be something the גמרא Gemara assumes is normally
done in the dark and you're having it in the light and
epilepsy is like falling asleep when you're supposed to be awake so
there's like a mixing there of you know daytime nighttime awake and
asleep I don't know. And again the issue that attitude things you
do during sex affects what happens to the kids. תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan. Our rabbis taught. המשמש מיטתו על מיטה שתינוק ישן עליה. Hamishmesh
mitato al mita shetinok yashen aleha.
If you have sex while on the same bed that an infant
is sleeping on while you're having sex. אותו תינוק נכפה. Oto tinok
nichpeh. That
infant so this is interesting this would be not the child that's
being conceived the child that's there will get epilepsy. ולאו אמרן אלא
דלא הוי בר שתא. Velo amran ela delo havei bar shata. That's
only if he is not I'm sorry בר שתא bar shata if
he is not a year old. אבל הוי בר שתא לית לן
בה. Aval havei bar shata leit lan bah. Once he's a year
old we don't have a problem with it which is funny I
mean you would think from a you know sort of a morality
perspective the older the child the bigger the problem right. So what
is it so again who knows you know what the גמרא's Gemara's
understanding if it's presumably understanding that's not just a morality issue it's
a שד shed issue whatever it is the younger the child is
the more vulnerable he is. ולאו אמרן אלא דגני להדי כרעיה. Velo
amran ela deganei lahadei krayeh. That's only if the child is sleeping
by your legs. אבל גני להדי רישיה לית לן בה. Aval ganei
lahadei reisheh leit lan bah. But if he's sleeping by the head
of the bed we don't have a problem. ולאו אמרן אלא דלא
מנח ידיה עלויה. Velo amran ela dela manach yadeih alaveih. It's also
only if you don't place your hand on the child I guess
while you're having sex. אבל מנח ידיה עלויה לית לן בה. Aval
manach yadeih alaveih leit lan bah. But if you place your hand
so you're like protecting the child we don't have a problem. So
presumably nakedness sex these types of things I don't know bring about
whatever spirits they are that can lead to epilepsy and therefore particularly
the infant here would be vulnerable. אל תצא יחידי בלילה. Al tetzei
yechidi balayla. It's interesting we're explaining this ברייתא braita we're working back
reverse order of the way it was said not the ברייתא braita
the teaching. Don't go out alone at night דתניא detanya as it's
taught לא יצא יחידי בלילה. lo yetzei yechidi balayla. Don't go out
alone at night לא בלילי רביעיות lo beleilei revi'iyot not nights of
Wednesday meaning Tuesday night ולא בלילי שבתות velo beleilei shabbatot
or Friday nights מפני mipnei because those were the nights we heard
before that the Friday nights and the Tuesday nights that were dangerous
nights for the שדים. shedim. מפני שאיגרת בת מחלת mipnei she'Igeret bat
Machlat because איגרת בת מחלת Igeret bat Machlat who is the queen
of the שדים shedim or something היא ושמונה עשרה ריבוא של מלאכי
חבלה hi ushmoneh esreh ribo shel malachei chabalah she and eighteen myriads
180,000
of angels of destruction יוצאים yotzim go out on Friday nights and
on Tuesday nights. Remember you weren't supposed to drink water on Friday
nights and Tuesday nights. וכל אחד ואחד יש לו רשות לחבל. Vechol
echad ve'echad yesh lo reshut lechabel. Every one of those 180,000 have
permission to to wreak havoc and destruction בפני עצמו bifnei atzmo individually.
Okay now מעיקרא Me'ikara now that doesn't seem to be our experience
of Tuesday nights and Friday nights so now the גמרא's Gemara's going
to say something about that. מעיקרא הוו שכיחי כולי יומא. Me'ikara havu
shechichi kulei yoma. Originally well actually we'll say anyway
originally these these demons were present
present every day. זימנא חדא פגע ברבי חנינא. Zimna chada paga beRabbi
Chanina. One day one day he met Rabbi Chanina. חנינא, Chanina, sorry,
בן דוסא. ben Dosa. So this, so the head,
the queen here, the queen demon, what's her name again? אגרת בת
מחלת Agrath bath Mahlath bumped into רבי חנינא בן דוסא. Rebbi Chanina
ben Dosa. אמרה ליה, Amra lei, she said to him: אילאו דמכרזי
עלך ברקיע, Ilav de-machrezi alach bi-rkia, if it were not that they
announce about you up in heaven, היזהרו בחנינא ובתורתו, Hizaheru be-Chanina u-ve-torato,
be careful about חנינא Chanina and his תורה, Torah, meaning that they
basically told me hands off about you up in heaven, that you're
such an important person I can't do anything about you against you,
זו סיכנתיך, Zo sikantich, I would have endangered you. I would have
brought harm to you. Here we're bumping into one another, how could
I not do harm to you? But you have special protection up
in heaven. אמר לה, Amar lah, he said to her: אי חשיבנא
ברקיע, I chashivna bi-rkia, if I am so important up in heaven,
so I got a little power here, better make sure to use
it. So
גוזר אני עלייך, Gozar ani alaichi, so I command regarding you, decree
regarding you, שלא תעברי ביישוב לעולם, she-lo ta'avri be-yishuv le-olam, that you
should never be able to pass through inhabited places. אמרה ליה, Amra
lei, she said to him: במטותא מינך, Bi-metuta minach, please,
I don't know exactly the idiomatic translation of that, but it's a
way of saying please,
at your leave please, שבק לי רווחא פורתא, shevok li ravcha purta,
give me a little breathing room. I mean, come on, how can
you exclude, exile me from the inhabited places? And I'm not clear
to me whether they needed, well I know, whether they needed this
space, do they need to hurt people? From other גמרות Gemarot and
even from here, it sounds a little bit like they're just סתם
stam living
around. But if we expose ourselves and we bump into them then
they're going to damage
it. Or are they like driven to hurt people? So she asks
for space because she needs living space, or she asks for space
because she needs an opportunity to actually hurt people? Not exactly clear
to me which one of those it is. How much we think
that they are... the line before says that each one has permission
to wreak destruction. It sounds like they're like hell-bent, excuse me, on
destruction. Not exactly clear if that was the thinking here. What?
Live in the house all the time and just damage each other.
Ah, well, that's true. Okay. So give me a little space. So
שבק לה לילי שבתות ולילי רביעיות. shevak lah leilei Shabatot u-leilei Revi'iot.
So he said, okay fine, Tuesday nights and Friday nights you can
go out. But the rest of the time you have to all
you שדים sheidim have to stay away from the inhabited places. I
don't know what to say. I don't know what to say. Okay.
ותו, Ve-tu, and in addition, now maybe Friday nights if it was
this way that it was sort of like human-decreed, you could maybe
understand Friday nights because people are at home on Friday nights so
nobody's going out as a general rule. Who knows? Okay. ותו. Ve-tu.
That would be the only non-market night.
Oh, that's interesting.
So that you're going and coming from market, Wednesday...
Ah, that's an interesting thought. Every other night is either before or
after a market day. Oh, okay. Good. ותו, Ve-tu, except for Saturday
night, but then you're going... you're going home from שול. shul. Okay.
ותו, Ve-tu, זימנא אחריתא, Zimna achrita, פגע ביה באביי. paga beih be-Abaye.
Now one time this head demoness bumped into אביי. Abaye. אמרה ליה,
Amra lei, she said to him: אילאו דמכרזי עלך ברקיע... Ilav de-machrezi
alach bi-rkia... you would think she would have learned her lesson about
giving away, divulging too much information. But she said to אביי, Abaye,
if it were not that they had announced about you up in
heaven, היזהרו בנחמני ובתורתו, Hizaheru be-Nachmani u-ve-torato, be careful about נחמני, Nachmani,
אביי Abaye was called נחמני Nachmani because he was
raised by and what's his name's house?
What? רבה
בר נחמני,
Rabbah bar
Nachmani, thank you. Be careful about נחמני ובתורתו Nachmani u-ve-torato and in
his house and his תורה, Torah, הוי סיכנתיך, havei sikantich, I would
have endangered you. אמר לה, Amar lah, he said to her: אי
חשיבנא ברקיע, I chashivna bi-rkia, if I'm so important up in heaven,
גוזרני עלייך, gozrani alaichi, I decree about you שלא תעברי ביישוב לעולם,
she-lo ta'avri be-yishuv le-olam, you should never. So that got her out
of even the Tuesday nights and the Friday nights and he presumably
was not sensitive to whatever complaint she raised afterwards. So the גמרא
Gemara says... so that explains why maybe it's not as prevalent as
it would seem from the initial discussion. So the גמרא Gemara says,
well, let's take a look. הכא חזינן דעברי, Hacha chazinan de-avri, what
do you mean that they don't? We see that there are still
שדים sheidim passing through in the inhabited places. So אמרי, Amri, so
you can respond by saying: הני גזייתא, hani gazyata, top of קב
עמוד א, kuf bet amud alef, נינהו, ninhu, that is, that's like
when they're going in the narrow, like in the alleyways, the שדים,
sheidim, yeah, דשמטי סוסייהו de-shamtei susaihu ואתו דברי להו, ve-atu davrei lehu,
that the horses, apparently they're also riding horses. I don't know if
they're riding their own, I don't know if they're riding invisible demon
horses or they're riding whatever visible this-worldly horses, but they're riding their
horses, they're in the alleyways and then they like be and then
the horses like bolt out because of the sense of I don't
know they pray or the demons encounter the horses, presumably the normal
horses, and the horses are scared and therefore the horses bolt out
and then the horses drag the demons with them. So they're not
going in יישוב, yishuv, they're only going in these like side alleys,
but then when they encounter like horses in those side alleys... Somehow
they get swept out of it. I don't know exactly.
So they have to go to the populated areas to bring them
back.
Yeah, so then for a while they can be in the populated
areas because the horses שלעפט shlepped them out. Something like that. I
don't know. אמר ליה Amar lei let's move on. אמר ליה Amar
lei רב Rav to רב אסי, Rav Assi, so רב Rav said
to רב אסי, Rav Assi, לא תדור במתא Lo tadur be-mata again
these type of like advice statements, don't live in a city דלא
צניפי סוסיא delo tzanifei susya that horses don't neigh in it. Why?
Because the רשב"ם Rashbam says if there are no horses in the
city then you are endangered from enemies. You know, you need horses
to run after enemies, to run away from enemies. You need good
transportation. I mean right, that was very critical, well that was with
the roads and the infrastructure. But anyway,
having fast transportation available is very critical. Don't live in a city
that doesn't have horses. ולא נבח בה כלבא velo navach bah kalba
or a city that doesn't have dogs barking, presumably guard dogs and
to warn you about impending
danger. ואל תדור בעיר ve-al tadur be-ir don't live in a
city, interesting, כפתא במתא kifta be-mata and בעיר. be-ir. I don't know,
maybe מתא mata is more of a village. Don't live in a
city דריש מתא אסיא de-reish mata asya but we're back to מתא
mata again, so I don't know. Anyway, דריש מתא אסיא de-reish mata
asya that the head of the city is an אסיא. asya. What's
an אסיא? asya? So אסיא asya is a doctor. So some say
it's the same as we said before, like if a תורה Torah
student, you know sage is going to spend too much time learning
תורה, Torah, the doctor is going to be too involved in his
medicine. You don't want somebody that's going to be distracted by these
heavy demands or outside interests and won't do a good job running
the city. Now some have the גרסא, girsa, in one גמרא Gemara
the גרסא girsa is דריש מתא אסי. de-reish mata Assi. It has
a little play because his word was רב אסי. Rav Assi. So
I wouldn't want you to be the head of my city, like
you should spend your time learning תורה Torah not trying to get
into
politics. Okay, ולא תנסיב תרתי velo tnasiv tarti don't marry two wives
at the same time, not sequentially. Because then they'll scheme against you.
וזוגות zugos I was thinking about that. ואי נסבת תרתי נסיב תלת
ve-i nasbat tarti nasiv telas and if you marry two, marry a
third one. So therefore if any two want to scheme against you,
at least presumably the third one will be an independent party and
she'll be able to warn you, protect you and so on. But
like I was thinking like Michael Zwel about the וזוגות zugos and
if you marry four then marry five. And it ran up to
a hundred and one and then it burst. Okay yeah.
No but I remember before don't go up against three, you know.
Right, that's true. I think his assumption is that that that it'd
be more likely that they'll fall out two against two than three
against one. Okay. So אמר ליה Amar lei רב Rav to רב
כהנא, Rav Kahana, רב Rav said to רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, הפוך
בנבילתא Hafoch bi-nevielta better you should turn over meaning involve yourself in
dead animal carcasses as a way of earning
money. ולא תיפוך במילי velo teifoch be-mili and don't spend your time
in talking and in words. You know maybe it means in gossip.
But not exactly clear you know what במילי be-mili he's trying to
you know sort of dissuade him from. But he's basically saying you
know you should go ahead and you can go get your hands
dirty and earn a living, even something that's means like you know
dealing with animal carcasses as we're back to see in a
moment. So פשוט נבילתא בשוקא Pshot nevielta be-shuka you should be prepared
to strip the carcass of the animal if you're dealing with like
you know animal carcasses and their leather and you're dealing with a
trade with them. To strip it in the marketplace ושקיל אגרא ve-shakil
agra and accept the you know payment for
it. ולא תימא velo teima and don't say
and this
presumably the words you should not be focusing on or dealing with,
rather do that than say כהנא אנא. Kahana ana. One minute, how
can I do such a job? I'm a כהן. Kohen. His name
is רב כהנא Rav Kahana so there's actually a question whether רב
כהנא Rav Kahana was really a כהן Kohen or not. Or he
just means כהנא Kahana is because it signifies כהונה kehuna and importance
even if he wasn't a כהן Kohen or was he a כהן
Kohen but right. Don't say I am כהנא Kahana or I am
a כהן Kohen וגברא רבא אנא ve-gavra raba ana I'm an important
person וסניא בי מילתא ve-sanya bi milta this is just despising for
me this is degrading for me. Don't say that, don't focus on
your status on your importance. You know good honest labor never never
does not degrade a person. So סלקת לאיגרא שירותך בהדך. salkas le-igra
sherusach be-hadach. So that's one thing about be prepared to do to
whatever work is necessary to earn a living. Now, even well סלקת
לאיגרא שירותך בהדך salkas le-igra sherusach be-hadach
if you're going up to a roof take your provisions with you.
Meaning don't go on a travel even presumably a small travel without
having food packed. And a דבר נאה davar na-eh my wife and
I always have this whenever we go on a whenever we go
on a trip. I always like pack like three meals like three
times as much food as I think we're going to need because
like and she and anyway she always packs like I think exactly
as much as she thinks we're going to need. Winds up that
if we listen to me we throw out half the food but
we're never anxious about not having anything to
eat. So anyway okay. So go up to the rooftop and take
your provisions with you even if you're at the you know just
going to the rooftop have your provisions with you. מאה קרי במתא
בזוזא me-ah karei be-mata be-zuza even if a hundred pumpkins—בעניינא דיומא—even b'inyana
d'yoma if...
even if a hundred pumpkins are going for a זוז, zuz, תותי
כנפיך ליהוו, Tuti knafecha lehavu, you should make sure that there's some
of them under your cloak. Meaning, even if you say, oh my
God, there's so much cheap food
around, and I can get it any time, make sure you have
your own provisions at home. Okay. אמר ליה רב לחייא בריה, Amar
lei Rav l'Chiya brei, Rav said to Chiya his son, לא תשתי
סמא, Lo tishti sama, very interesting,
do not drink like drugs, I mean סמא, sama, you know, could
mean some type of a medical potions, but it's quite fascinating, if
you take a look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, I just got to
read this to you, five lines down in the רשב"ם Rashbam where
the רשב"ם Rashbam begins at the bottom of the page, לא תשתי
סמא, Lo tishti sama, he says אל תשת סמים, Al tisht samim,
סמים samim is the current is the Hebrew word for drugs, מפני
שנקבע להם וסת, mipnei shenikva lahem veset,
because you'll get addicted to them is essentially what he means, there'll
be a you know a pattern, you'll need them, your body will
become addicted to them, וליבך שוחא, v'libcha shocha, you'll always be wanting
them, you'll always be sort of desiring them, your heart will always
be asking for them, ותכלה מעות, v'tachle maot, and it'll lead to
ultimately you know your take away you know all of your money
will go after them, ואפילו לרפואה לא תשתי אם אפשר ברווחא אחרינא,
va'afilu l'refuah lo tishti im efshar beravcha achrina, so don't even take
them for you know for medical purposes, you know people get hooked
when they have to take pain medication, oxycontin and you know other
types of pain medication, so it's quite fascinating you know that the
רשב"ם Rashbam understands that we're talking about a type of drugs that
can lead to certain addictions, I mean I don't know if we're
talking about the same type of narcotics we're talking about but drugs
that can lead to certain addictions, ולא תשוור ניגרא, Velo tishvar nigra,
do not step like wide, which he says means either just don't
go running you know taking wide steps because that's supposed to hurt
your eyesight or jump over, it maybe means jump over like canals
of water, isn't it פסיעה גסה? psiah gassah?
No, according to the first explanation, but anyway this is in Aramaic,
ולא תעקר ככא, Velo ta'aker kakka, do not remove teeth, if you
have a toothache, don't you know and don't try to do some
other way of dealing with it medically before you pull it out,
although one I don't know what the story was you know in
ancient at those times I imagine it would be quite easy for
it to become infected if you didn't pull it out, I don't
know if pulling it out did any better, so anyway don't pull
out your teeth you know unless absolutely necessary, ולא תקנא בחיויא, Velo
tiknei b'chivya,
do not do not provoke a snake, we had snakes earlier, don't
provoke a snake, ולא תקנא בארמאה, Velo tiknei b'arma'ah, and don't provoke
an Aramean or an Aramean woman, so these are people that if
you provoke them or things that if you provoke them will be
able to get back at you, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, our Rabbis
taught, ג' אין מתקנאים בהם, Gimmel ein mitkana'im bahem, there are three
that you do not provoke, ואלו הן, v'eilu hen, and these are
they, נכרי קטן, nochri katan, a minor non-Jew, or a small but
presumably it means minor, ונחש קטן, v'nachash katan, a small snake, or
presumably also like a young baby snake, ותלמיד קטן, v'talmid katan, and
a young student, מאי
טעמא, mai ta'ama, why is that, דמלכותייהו אחורי אודנייהו יתיב, d'malchuteihu achorei
udneihu yativ, their kingship is behind their ears, meaning that they will
in a brief period of time you know become have power and
they will be able to hurt you and get back at you
if you do something to them when they are young, כל
שכן kal v'chomer when they're older but don't think they're young and
you get away with it, right? It's like what was that? The
Godfather 2? Remember when they left over the one kid? No? I
don't know what I'm talking about? No? Wasn't it the guy anyway
whatever, the guy who became the guy whatever, all right, you'll do
your חזרה chazarah there, anyway, אמר ליה רב לאיבו בריה, Amar lei
Rav l'Aivo brei, Rav said to Aivo his son, טרחי בך בשמעתא
טובא ולא מסתייע, Tarchi bach b'shma'ata tuva v'lo mistayei, I see you're
putting a lot of effort into your learning and it's not מצליח
matzliach נעבעך nebach you're not being successful in your learning, right? We
haven't heard about an
איבו Aivo as an אמורא, Amora, he had a son איבו, Aivo,
he נעבעך nebach it's not going well for you in your learning,
ולא מסתייע מילתא, v'lo mistayei milta, תא אגמרך מילי דעלמא, Ta agmarcha
milei d'alma, come let me teach you some of the ways of
the world, let me give you some business advice, maybe you should
go ahead and go into business instead, I'll give you some business
advice, אדחלא אכרעיך, Ad-chala achraeicha, while the sand is still on your
legs, זבינך זבין, zvincha zavin, sell your wares, meaning if you went
traveling and you're you know like you know going to other places
and buying wares, bringing them back and selling them, don't tarry to
sell what you've brought in, as soon as you know even while
the you haven't washed off your legs, you just arrived, sell your
wares as quickly as possible and then turn around and go and
get you know and then repeat the trip, don't wait to get
like the absolute best price, כל מילי זבין ותחרט, Kol milei zavin
v'techaret, you could sell anything and justifiably have regret if you found
out you know if afterwards you feel oh my gosh I should
have you know I could have gotten a better price whatever, that
would make sense, בר מחמרא דזבין ולא תחרט, Bar mechmra d'zvin v'lo
techaret, but wine is the one thing you should never regret having
sold at a lesser price because by the time you would have
gotten around to selling it maybe it would have turned into vinegar
it would have spoiled, it is interesting though on the one hand
telling him on the one hand telling him sell your stuff immediately
but then pointing out to him it's possible you will have some
regret, בר מחמרא דזבין ולא תחרט, Bar mechmra d'zvin v'lo techaret, שרי
כיסך פתח. Sharei kisecha ptach. פתח סקיך. ptach sakeikha. So first open
up your money pouch and then open up your bag of wares,
meaning first get payment for the goods before you deliver them. Okay,
if the other guy is willing to go along.
Okay. Exactly, exactly. Just whenever there's any debate in terms of the
conditions or what exactly happened, if you're the one holding on to
the money or you're in a better
position. Right. Okay, פתח סקיך. ptach sakeikha. קבא מארעא ולא כורא מאיגרא.
kava me'ara velo kura me'igra. Better to have a large measure from
the ground and not a small measure from the roof. So what
does this mean? So the Rashbam says what that means is
better to have your business dealings close rather than far away. Even
if you go far away you think that you can... let me
take a
look. קבא מארעא... kava me'ara... מוטב שיהיה למקום קרוב להשתכר דבר. mutav
sheyihiyeh lemakom karov lehistaher davar. I'm sorry, I said it the reverse.
A small measure from the ground rather than a large measure from
the roof. And better you should not have to travel far even
if the profit margin is less rather than traveling far for a
potentially larger profit
margin. Okay. תמרי בחלוזך, tamrei bechalozach, your dates in your basket, לבי
סודנא רהיט. levei sudna rahit. If there are dates in your basket,
run to the brewers, the person who makes the mead, the beer.
Don't let them sit in the basket and spoil or use them
in the basket for eating purposes. No, what you should do with
dates is as soon as you get them in the basket, go
ahead and make it into beer and you'll make a good profit.
Beer is the safest form, we don't know?
Right. ועד כמה, v'ad kama, and how many dates until what point?
אמר רבא עד תלתא סא, amar Rava ad tlata sa, until three
sa. I guess after that maybe you don't need to, I don't
know what it means after that. After that you're not afraid
that they'll all get eaten up, you'll have enough left over, you
can eat some and then you'll have enough left over to make
the beer.
Or he's saying even with a little amount, you're saying even with
a little amount go make...
No, I think תלתא סא tlata sa is even up to a
large amount, more than that you don't I think means you don't
have to worry because otherwise if you leave it in the basket
it'll get eaten. More than that, so if some get eaten you'll
still have enough for making the beer. אמר רב פפא amar Rav
Papa אי לאו דרמינא שיכרא, ei lav deramina shikra, Rav Papa said,
if I had not gone into the beer business, לא איעתרי, lo
i'atarei, I would not have been rich. איכא דאמרי אמר רב חסדא,
ika d'amri amar Rav Chisda, some say Rav Chisda said, אי לאו
דרמינא שיכרא לא איעתרי. ei lav deramina shikra lo i'atarei. So he
also went into the beer business, so one of them said this.
Had I not gone into this business of making beer I would
not have become rich. מאי סודנא? mai sudna? What's the meaning of
the word סודנא sudna which is basically the Aramaic word for the
brewers, the place where they make the beer? אמר רב חסדא סוד
נאה, amar Rav Chisda sod na'eh,
it's a very nice secret. So meaning presumably that either the way
of making it is a secret or it's a secret how profitable
it is, people don't appreciate how profitable it is and it's a
good thing to be aware of. It could also be that it's
secret because people assume dates are for eating and the whole point
was no, you got dates in your basket, go make beer out
of it, go use it for something more valuable.
It's interesting that the word for drink in English is soda.
Oh, I think that is a complete coincidence. Okay.
סוד נאה וגמילות חסדים.
sod na'eh
ugemilut chasadim. Now
I don't know how the גמילות חסדים gemilut chasadim fits into the
word סודנא, sudna, but anyway, it also allows for acts of kindness.
רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. Oh, I think it's a play on רב
חסדא. Rav Chisda. Oh, that's a very... oh, רב חסדא גמילות חסדים.
Rav Chisda gemilut chasadim. Oh, that's very nice, very nice. I hadn't
thought about that. Okay, and you can do good with it because
you know if you make money then you can do philanthropy. אמר
רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, כל אגב, kol agav, so said Rav
Papa, this is the one who went into the beer business, anyway
here's some business advice from Rav Papa. כל אגב גבי בעי. kol
agav gavi ba'ei. Any אגב, agav, אגב agav means like due to,
because of. Some say it's a way of referring to things that
have to be written up as a contract, like just in case
to keep you honest we'll write a contract. It could also mean
that a way of putting a lien on land is you can
put a lien on chattel sort of, indirectly אגב agav through the
lien on the land. So things that involve liens and
contracts, don't assume it's money in the bank. גבי בעי, gavi ba'ei,
they still have to be
collected. Like מטלטלי אגב מקרקעי, metaltalei agav mekarkei, right. So you know
so it could particularly mean that he's talking about that and he's
saying even chattel that has a lien is particularly difficult because you
don't know where the chattel is. But anyway, any loans and notes
are dangerous investments, they still need to be collected. כל אשראי, kol
ashrai, anything that is basically on credit, ספק אתי ספק לא אתי.
safek ati safek lo ati. You don't even know if you'll ever
get paid for it, they didn't have PayPal. ודאתי מוס רבני מניה
ved'ati mus ravnei mineih and even if you get it maybe it'll
be bad or it will be bad money meaning you'll get paid
maybe bit by bit you won't get paid all at one
time. So it's not good business to have to have notes out
and lend money out and so on. ג' דברים אמר רבי יוחנן.
gimmel devarim amar Rabbi Yochanan. He was also somebody who was in
the beer business, maybe people tried to buy from him on credit
and he's saying
don't sell on credit if you're in the wholesale business. ג' דברים
אמר רבי יוחנן משום אנשי ירושלים, gimmel devarim amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum
anshei Yerushalayim,
three things Rabbi Yochanan said in the name of the people of
Jerusalem. כשאתה יוצא למלחמה אל תצא בראשונה אלא תצא באחרונה. keshe'ata yotze
lemilchama al tetze berishona ela tetze be'achrona.
If you're going out to war don't go in the front lines,
go in the rear guard, in the supporting troops in the back.
כדי שתכנס בראשונה kedei shetikanes berishona so that you can come in
first. first? Why? Because if when you're... if... if you're retreating
you'll be the closest to get back. I mean, you know, the
מהרש"א Maharsha says why didn't he just say because if you're in
the front lines you'll get get killed first? So I don't know.
ועשה שבתך חול ואל תצטרך לבריות. Va'aseh Shabat-cha Chol Ve'al Titztarech Labriyot.
So interesting, before we had this Rabbi Akiva, now Rabbi Yochanan is
saying it later than Rabbi Akiva, make your Shabbos a weekday, you
know, he's embracing this statement of Rabbi Akiva's and do not, you
know, become dependent on other people. והוי משתדל עם מי שהשעה משחקת
לו Vehevay Mishtadel Im Mi Shehasha'ah Mesacheket Lo also like we saw
by Rabbi Akiva before, so maybe there were different traditions who said
it. You know, anyway try to get chummy and try to, you
know, get close to somebody who is having very good fortune. Okay,
אמר רבי... Amar Rabi...
now or is there a question here if there's an introduction to
this or just a start to it? שלושה דברים אמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי משום אנשי ירושלים. Shlosha Devarim Amar Rabi Yehoshua Ben Levi
Mishum Anshei Yerushalayim. Three things Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi said in the
name of the people of Jerusalem. אל תרבה בגנות משום מעשה שהיה.
Al Tarbe Begnut Mishum Ma'aseh Shehayah. By the way
oh maybe actually that's part of the answer that Rabbi Yochanan wasn't
saying it himself, he was saying it in the name of אנשי
ירושלים. Anshei Yerushalayim. So maybe אנשי ירושלים Anshei Yerushalayim learned it from
Rabbi Akiva or maybe Rabbi Akiva learned it from אנשי ירושלים. Anshei
Yerushalayim. But anyway it makes sense why... I have no idea. The
elders, the wise people, the general... like a general wisdom that was
going on. But anyway, but given that it's not in their own
name, you can understand that Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi Yochanan might have,
you know, similar sources. So anyway, three things Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi
says in the name of the people of Jerusalem: אל תרבה בגנות
משום מעשה שהיה. Al Tarbe Begnut Mishum Ma'aseh Shehayah. Do not have
too much... do things that are גנות gnut like which is like
embarrassing or
shameful because of the event that happened. I'm getting to that in
a minute. Okay, now what is that... what is that type of
shameful thing? So the גמרא Gemara is going to say it's the
story of דוד ובתשבע David UVatsheva that she was up and bathing
on the rooftop, so it's a type of a thing being naked
that you should, you know, do more in privacy. But if you
look at the side and the רשב"ם Rashbam says the real גירסא
girsa should be אל תרבה בגגות. Al Tirbe Begagot. Don't do things
up on the rooftops
משום מעשה שהיה. Mishum Ma'aseh Shehayah. It's like, you know, just don't
do things in... think you're going to be in private that you're
up on the rooftop, people can see what you're doing on the
rooftop too.
Okay, so people can see of course they say
instead of גנות gnut they say גגות. gagot. I understand but it's
not how the רשב"ם Rashbam understands it. Okay, and it wasn't in
a garden, it was on a rooftop. Okay, משום מעשה שהיה. Mishum
Ma'aseh Shehayah. בתך בגרה, Bitcha Bagra, if your daughter has become mature,
she's now of marriageable age at 12 and a half, so שחרר
shichrer and you know and so she's... men are interested in her,
maybe she's also, you know, is
now... has more interest in men or boys. So anyway שחרר עבדך
ותן לה. Shachrer Avdecha Veten Lah. So get her married right away.
So first of all you got a slave around the house, don't
have your... don't have your slave there with your... with your teenage
daughter. So what you should do is free your slave and... and
marry... and marry her off to him. Now I don't know if
the slave is interested in her or she's interested in the slave,
you're not in a position to force the slave who you're going
to marry, maybe it's a condition of freedom, I don't know. Anyway
the point being... be careful about once they become sexually
aware. You know, not interesting because the גמרא's Gemara different treatment about,
you know, sort of adolescent boys and adolescent girls. The גמרא Gemara
says that, you know, when you're you know when you're 13, 15,
18 you should get married, talking to men or you know teenage
boys, because of your sexual desires. So it's the same type of
a concern but here obviously in a patriarchal society it's really saying
to the father marry her off as opposed to when it speaks
to the boys, you know, to the young men it says get
married at... at a young
age. Okay, והוי זהיר באשתך מחתנה ראשון. Vehevay Zahir Be'ishtcha Mechatanah Rishon.
Be careful with your wife regarding her first son-in-law. So what does
that mean? So obviously there's obviously all three of these statements if
the... if the first one was about דוד ובתשבע David UVatsheva have
to do with you know
sexual... sexual desire. So let's see how the גמרא Gemara explains
this. מאי טעמא? Mai Ta'ama? What's the reason? חד אמר Chad Amar
משום ערווה, Mishum Ervah, which again fits into the pattern, you know,
maybe she's... maybe she'll find an opportunity to have an affair with
him. So you should be
careful. וחד אמר Vechad Amar משום ממון. Mishum Mamon. Maybe she'll... no
she's so happy that her daughter is... is married or first one,
that she'll spend a lot of money
on him giving him gifts or something. So the גמרא Gemara says
והא והא איתנהו Veha Veha Itnehu and you know what both of
those are concerns. So again, you know, it's interesting because the גמרא
Gemara is often, you know, concerned about men using opportunities to, you
know, that for... you know, for sexual liaisons. But again here it's
focus is, you know, as I said, the sort of patriarchal focus
is not that the concern is unique to women of this type
of behavior but it's telling basically the father or the husband who's
the one in control, you have to watch over
them. אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabi Yochanan. Said Rabbi Yochanan. שלושה מנוחלי
העולם הבא. Shlosha Menochalei Ha'olam Haba. There are three people... no they
will inherit the world to come. אלו הן Elu Hen and these
are they. הדר בארץ ישראל, Hadar Be'eretz Yisrael, one who lives in
Israel, והמגדל בניו לתלמוד תורה, Vehamigadel Banav Letalmud Torah, Rabbi Yochanan lived
in Israel, והמגדל בניו לתלמוד תורה Vehamigadel Banav Letalmud Torah if you
raise your children to learn Torah. What?
That was a תלמיד חכם.
talmid chacham. Oh good point. That was a תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham.
והמבדיל על היין במוצאי שבתות v'hamavdil al hayayin b'motza'ei shabbatot and if
you make הבדלה Havdalah on wine on מוצאי שבת Motzei Shabbos so
you know so what's the big deal everybody makes הבדלה? Havdalah? Now
the big deal first of all we'll see what the גמרא Gemara
says but if you remember for the גמרא Gemara it was a
חידוש chiddush that even though you made הבדלה Havdalah at home you
have to go ahead and make הבדלה Havdalah again you know
על הכוס. al hakos. The גמרא Gemara you know the גמרא Gemara
said אשמע מינה ashma mina it's not enough to make הבדלה Havdalah
in שול. shul. So one thing he might be saying is you're
מקפיד makpid not just to be יוצא yotzei with the הבדלה Havdalah
in שול shul you're going back and you're making הבדלה על הכוס.
Havdalah al hakos. He also could mean like our earlier discussion of
חמרא מדינה chamra medina that you're מקפיד makpid to do it on
wine. Those I think would have been two reasonable interpretations of why
this is a חידוש chiddush but the גמרא Gemara says מאי היא
mai hi what does it mean that it's what's the special thing
of
הבדלה Havdalah on wine? דמשייר מקידושא לאבדלתא d'mishayer mikiddusha l'avdalta that you
leave over from קידוש Kiddush to הבדלה Havdalah which again what the
what the way תוספות Tosafot explains it the רשב"ם Rashbam also but
תוספות Tosafot elaborates it means if you have a limited amount of
wine you don't drink it all up at קידוש Kiddush you leave
some of the wine over from קידוש Kiddush presumably you have some
water or wine you could add to it so it's not a
כוס פגום kos pagum but you made sure that you're going to
have wine at הבדלה Havdalah by and even if it means leaving
over from קידוש. Kiddush. Now that leads to the question of well
if you don't have so much wine and you need it for
הבדלה Havdalah why not just make קידוש Kiddush on bread? And that
you know and that gets back to this big discussion of is
קידוש Kiddush on bread really seen as an as an equivalent alternative
or something only in an extreme בדיעבד? bedi'avad? So there's like a
whole מהרש"א Maharsha that discusses a very you know there's a complicated
תוספות Tosafot here I'm not sure if I've exactly clear what he's
saying. Anyway it leads to this whole discussion of what do you
do if you don't have a lot of wine and the מהרש"א
Maharsha says seems very clear to him you based on this גמרא
Gemara you use it for קידוש Kiddush you don't say oh well
we'll save it for הבדלה Havdalah and just make קידוש Kiddush on
bread. So you use it for קידוש Kiddush if you can
save some for הבדלה Havdalah great yes. Didn't רבי יוחנן'ס Rabbi Yochanan's
sons die young?
That's an excellent point. Yes רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had ten children
they all died young so maybe he's trying to sort of talk
about you know that but that they get עולם הבא olam haba
but they were too young to be מגדל בניו לתלמוד תורה megadel
banav l'talmud torah but they did live in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
It is interesting though the three things here you know are about
קודש kodesh and חול chol if you think about it right? The
connection to הבדלה Havdalah right? You're living in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
not in חוץ לארץ Chutz L'Aretz which is non-holy land. You're you
know you're raising your children for תלמוד תורה talmud torah and presumably
means you know one wonders if מגדל לתלמוד תורה megadel l'talmud torah
means that they would go they're going into תורה Torah as a
profession or does it just mean that you are teaching them תורה
Torah you know and you know to be to be learned? But
it could mean that you're actually teaching them to invest their lives
in תורה Torah and then it's also separating as it were between
קודש kodesh and חול. chol. So I think these these three fit
into the theme at the end about the הבדלה. Havdalah.
Yeah the הבדלה Havdalah in שול shul so to speak is the
עמידה. Amidah.
Yeah not not like no no no not the thing that we
do now out no no no when the גמרא Gemara says you
have to repeat it means you said it in דאבנינג davening you
said it in שמונה עשרה. shmoneh esrei. Okay so anyway alright and
that might be why you get עולם הבא olam haba you know
you separated out for קודש kodesh your life or you know the
way you live for קודש kodesh purposes and therefore you also will
get something of the
afterlife. Yes טוב.
tov. Well it's interesting because מהרש"א Maharsha says that that the focus
is on raising your children for תלמוד תורה talmud torah not
on them actually having succeeding right? That's true too. So then it's
about him. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan שלושה מכריז עליהן הקדוש
ברוך הוא בכל יום. shlosha machriz aleihen hakadosh baruch hu bechol yom.
Three people God makes proclamations about them each day presumably that they're
good guys. The מהרש"א Maharsha repeat says that it ties into like
the story before about רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina you know that they
say up in heaven hey be careful about these people to the
demons don't touch them they're very important. So anyway who are the
three that are so important that they get an announcement made about
them in heaven? So על רווק הדר בכרך ואינו חוטא, al ravak
hadar bikrach v'eino chotei, a single man now we're getting into men
with sexual desire you know issue about their sexual drives so who
lives in a city and doesn't sin doesn't you know go to
prostitutes or unmarried women certainly not married women anyway he remains celibate
and particularly it's in a city because there are plenty of opportunities
in a city that there aren't in a village. ואינו חוטא. v'eino
chotei. ועל עני המחזיר אבידה לבעליה, v'al ani hamachzir aveida l'va'aleha,
a poor person who returns a lost object to the owner so
people that have like a strong יצר הרע yeitzer hara and still
do the right thing. Either יצר הרע yeitzer hara for sex or
יצר הרע yeitzer hara for for money or a need for money
and still returns it to the to the owners. ועל עשיר המעשר
פירותיו v'al ashir ham'aser peirotav
and then a rich person when he takes his מעשר ma'aser from
his fruits בצינעה b'tzina he does it in private so we're not
concerned that he's not going to take מעשר ma'aser but his what
his יצר הרע yeitzer hara would be is the גאווה ga'avah to
call attention oh look at all this I'm giving to the לוי
Levi a million dollars מעשר ma'aser I gave to the לוי Levi
this year. No if you do it in private also that's conquering
over another very strong desire and that's a huge accomplishment. רב ספרא
רווק הדר בכרך הוה Rav Safra ravak hadar bikrach hava
now רב ספרא Rav Safra was a single man living in a
כרך. krach. A כרך krach was even bigger than an עיר. ir.
כרך Krach is like a metropolis he was living in New York
City plenty of opportunities to sin in New York City. So תני
תנא קמיה דרבא. tani tana kamei d'Rava. תני תנא קמיה דרבא רב
ספרא tanni tanna kammai de-Rava Rav Safra so that's the background. Now
the תנא tanna taught what we just said in the presence of
רבא Rava and רב ספרא, Rav Safra, if a single person lives
in a city they get a proclamation about them in heaven and
they don't sin. So צהבו פניו דרב ספרא. tzahavu panav de-Rav Safra.
So רב ספרא's Rav Safra face lit up. Oh, it's great, they're
talking about me up in heaven, I'm such a good guy. אמר
ליה רבא amar leh Rava so רבא Rava said to him, לאו
כגון מר. lav kigon mar. We're not talking about like you. Okay,
you don't count. אלא ella doesn't mean because you're so righteous, it's
not a big deal. But don't think your accomplishment is so great.
Who do they announce about in heaven? כגון רב חנינא ורב אושעיא,
kigon Rav Hanina ve-Rav Oshaya, like רב חנינא Rav Hanina and רב
אושעיא, Rav Oshaya, דהוו אושכפי בארעא דישראל. de-havu ushchafi be-ara de-Yisrael. They
were cobblers, they were shoemakers in the land of Israel. ודהוו יתבי
בשוקא דזונות ve-de-havu yasvi be-shuka de-zonos
and their shop would be in the marketplace there right by the
harlots, you
know, right by the, you know, whatever, right by the brothel, what's
it called? Brothel. Right by the brothel, in the red light district
exactly. ועבדי להו מסאני לזונות ve-avdu lehu masani le-zonos and they would
make shoes
for the prostitutes, ועיילי להו ve-ayli lehu and they'd bring them into
the brothel to deliver
their shoes. אינהו מסתכלי בהו inhu mistakli behu ואינהו, ve-inhu, the prostitutes
would look at them, at the
rabbis, ואינהו לא מדלו עינייהו לאסתכולי בהו, ve-inhu lo madlu einaihu le-istakulei
behu, but they would keep their eyes to the ground and would
not look up, you know, even in talking to the prostitutes, they'd
keep their eyes averted. וכי משתבעי הכי ve-chi mishtavei hachi and the
prostitutes when they would take an oath, would take an oath in
the following way: בחייהון דרבנן קדישי דבארעא דישראל. be-hayeihon de-rabbanan kaddishei de-be-ara
de-Yisrael. They'd take an oath in the name of the holy rabbis
of the land of Israel. They were so impressed by their behavior.
So that's who they get announced about in heaven, not
you. Alright. Now, excuse me, they were
in the trade, maybe מסייע עובדי
עבירה?
mesaye'a
ovdei aveira?
I'm not going to have this
conversation.
Yes, it's okay, yeah, I, alright. Who says it was מסייע? mesaye'a?
I don't know, that's a good question.
רב חנינא ורב
אושעיא,
Rav Hanina
ve-Rav
Oshaya, what, they were not married?
They never,
I don't know, that at this time they weren't married, presumably at
this time they were single. Michael, I don't know that it was
מסייע עובדי עבירה, mesaye'a ovdei aveira, maybe it was their walking shoes,
walking shoes as opposed to something else. Or maybe it was a
shoe for going out, number one. Number two is it okay within
the context of that question, right, there's a general issue about types
of things that can easily be purchased elsewhere, that doesn't mean that
you can't sell them, you know, because anybody could just go next
door and get them from somewhere else.
But listen to what they said, they said קדישי דארעא, kaddishei de-ara,
they were
learned, right, the שבת Shabbat shoes. Alright. I think that although the
גמרא Gemara here has them talking Aramaic, you know, again, I'm guessing
that we're talking about that they were Roman. Anyway, but שלשה הקדוש
ברוך הוא אוהבן, shelosha HaKadosh Baruch Hu ohavan, three God loves them.
מי שאינו כועס, mi she-eino ko'es, interesting different types of categories. You'll
get עולם הבא, Olam Ha-Ba, they announce about you in heaven, clearly
that was about conquering your desires, having mastery of your desires. Now
three are loved by God. מי שאינו כועס, mi she-eino ko'es, somebody
who doesn't get angry, ומי שאינו משתכר, u-mi she-eino mishtaker,
somebody who doesn't get drunk, ומי שאינו מעמיד על מדותיו, ve-mi she-eino
ma'amid al middosav,
somebody who does not sort of, you know, sort of stand by
his, not principles, but stand by his, like on his honor,
meaning that you're not so offended when somebody does something or says
something wrong to you that you have to like take it back
out of them. You're willing to be מוחל mochel if people somehow
verbally mistreat you or do wrong things to you.
Stand on
ceremony might be a way of saying it, well ceremony's a little
different point, but anyway, somebody who's not so מקפיד, makpid, that's the
good English word. Anyway, okay. The מהרש"א Maharsha says a beautiful thing,
he says these three things are basically about decent behavior between people.
So he quotes the line in פרקי אבות Pirkei Avos that says
that, you know, who is loved to heaven is the one who
is loved among by other
people. So these three that God loves are the three that act
in decent ways in their interactions with other people, doesn't get other
people angry at them. שלשה הקדוש ברוך הוא שונאן, shelosha HaKadosh Baruch
Hu sonei'an, three God hates. And also we can see that so
much of this is going to have to do with how you
interact with people and whether you're a מענטש mentsh or not. So
three God hates: המדבר אחד בפה ואחד בלב, ha-medabber echad ba-peh ve-echad
ba-lev,
you say one thing in your mouth but say another thing, think
another thing in your heart, your duplicitousness. והיודע עדות בחברו ואינו מעיד
לו, ve-ha-yodei'a eidut be-havero ve-eino me'ido lo,
you know testimony for your friend and you do not come to
testify for him in court. You know, I don't want to get
involved. והרואה דבר ערוה בחברו ומעיד בו
יחידי. ve-ha-ro'eh davar erva be-havero u-me'id bo yehidi. So, this is בו
bo as opposed to לו, lo, that you see your friend
doing some type of a sexual sin and you testify against him,
not for him, against him, but you're the only single witness. And
because, you know, testimony in these types of issues as opposed to
monetary issues, anything less than two witnesses was completely rejected out of
court, had no weight. In monetary
matters one witness has some weight, whereas in other areas, sexual... status
matters and so on with less than one witness has you know
less than two witnesses has no weight. So you go you testify
against him by yourself, that's only going to be—that's not going to
accomplish any good and it'll lead to bad. Let's take a look.
So let's wait, I mean let's read a little bit more. כי
הא דטוביה חטא, Ki ha deTuvya chata, Tuvya sinned, presumably he had,
you know, some sexual sin, married woman, whatever it was. ואתא זיגוד
לחודיה, Va’ata Zigud lechudei, Zigud
came by himself, ואתא בי קמי דרב פפא, va’ata beikamei deRav Pappa,
and gave testimony about him in front of Rav Pappa that he
should know this person sinned, whatever they were going to do to
him, you know, so it’s quite interesting. What could they do? It
wasn’t at a time when they gave מלקות, malkus, but so even
that’s fascinating, like whatever sort of communal, you know, types of discipline
that they would use, and even there they’re מקפיד makpid in terms
of the formal rule of two witnesses. So he gave he testified
about him to Rav Pappa. נגדיה לזיגוד, Nagdei leZigud, so Rav Pappa
gave lashes not
to—yeah but the נגדיה, nagdei, right, since this is not the biblical
lashes, but yes it’s a type of a, you know, it’s a
type of a rabbinic lashes. So he gave these lashes to Zigud
the one he testified, not the one who did the deed. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, טוביה חטא וזיגוד מינגד? Tuvya
chata veZigud minged? So Tuvya sins and Zigud gets lashes? So it’s
also very interesting though, you know, טוביה Tuvya is like טוב tov
and you know, so he’s good or whatever, and זיגוד Zigud and
מינגד minged very similar words too. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei, he
said to him, אין, in, yes, דכתיב לא יקום עד אחד באיש,
dechetiv lo yakum ed echad be’ish, one witness cannot testify against a
person, meaning in issues of personal matters as opposed to monetary matters.
ואת לחודיך אסהדת ביה, Ve’at lechudach asda’at bei, you gave testimony by
yourself. שם רע בעלמא קמפקת ביה, Shem ra be’alma kamafket bei, you’re
just spreading, you know, evil report about him. מוציא שם רע, Motzi
shem ra, meaning that this is, you’re libeling him, and
it’s not—what you said is not believed, so the only effect it’s
going to have is going to give this person, you know, ill
repute. Now of course the problem here is translating this into nowadays
is, you know, particularly about issues which sadly we deal, we, you
know, we have to deal with on a—it seems like a regular
basis it should, but but anyway, you know, concerns about sexual abuse
and that some—and you know it’s a real issue about how to
handle it because people can make accusations that are completely unfounded and
can destroy a person’s life even if afterwards they retract it and
we have to, you know, and there’s and there’s on the one
hand, you know, there’s I think that there’s like two types of
responses in the community when these things come up. One is to
completely silence them, which is something that’s, you know, I think not
as much the response within our community, and the other response might
be—but it sometimes is—and the other is to like totally like, you
know, jump on them and and and you know believe them and
attack the person who’s they’re being set up against, etc. And both
of those are not responsible because, you know, people can make false
accusations and it can destroy people’s lives. How to exactly know how
to balance those possibilities, you know obviously you also have to do
your utmost to protect potential innocent people, so you know and whether
but often one of the ways in which you know whether
you’re you’re you’re going down the right path are there other people
have reported similar types of things, you know, as opposed to if
just one person says it, it makes it more dangerous, you know,
how to respond to those types of things. So I think that
that’s really in a way what’s being said here, you know, that
if it’s just one person we can’t trust it and it could
destroy, you know, and it could be totally destructive on the other
hand you can’t completely dismiss it either, I don’t think you go
and give lashes when one person comes away comes along and reports
sexual abuse, you know, you have to weigh it very seriously but
exactly how you do that balancing act is like I think a
real—requires real wisdom.
What, someone who is married doesn't it make it אסורה asura to
her husband?
Yeah well the question is that again, but how can you do
that with less than sufficient witnesses?
Didn’t we learn about the סוטה Sotah that she’s אסורה asura to
her husband?
Yeah but you need two witnesses there, you know, so at least
two, yes, but it has to be done with the right types
of witnesses. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, just to
finish up this point: אמר רבי שמואל בר רב יצחק אמר רב:
Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar
Rav Yitzchak amar Rav: מותר לשנאותו. Mutar lesano’aso.
If you see this about a person even though you should not
go talking about it because it won’t do any good and it’ll
just lead to an evil—you know to an evil repute, but you
who know it’s true, you can hate this person. שנאמר, Shene’emar, you
know you can own your know you can own your own what
you’ve seen yourself. שנאמר כי תראה חמור שונאך רובץ תחת משאו, Shene’emar
ki tireh chamor sona’acha rovetz tachat masa’o,
if you see the donkey of your—the one of somebody you hate
struggling under its burden. So מאי שונא? mai sonay? What type of
person would you be hating? Presumably this you’re legitimately hating this person.
What’s the context? אילימא שונא נכרי, Ileima sonay nochri, if it’s a
non-Jew, והתניא שונא שאמרו שונא ישראל ולא שונא נכרי, vehatania sonay she’amru
sonay Yisrael velo sonay nochri, the פסוק pasuk is talking about a
Jew who you hate and not about a non-Jew, and
that’s in a discussion about the mitzvah of פריקה וטעינה, prika ute’ina,
of unloading the animal and so on, who does it apply to?
אלא פשיטא שונא ישראל, Ela peshita sonay Yisrael, we’re talking about a
Jew that you hate. ומי שרי למסניה? Umi shari lesanya? How are
you allowed to hate him?
Don't hate your fellow Jew. אלא *Ella*, right, so it could be
you're talking, okay, you're not a good guy, you hate somebody you're
not supposed to hate. And even so, but the גמרא *Gemara* is
assuming that we're talking not
about proper behavior. So you're hating him in a case where you're
allowed to. What's the scenario? אלא דאיכא סהדי דעביד איסורא *Ella de'ika
sahadi de'avid issura*, maybe there are witnesses that he's done
prohibitions and disregarded the law and therefore you're allowed to hate him.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says if there are witnesses כולי עלמא נמי
מסני סני ליה *kuly alma nami misne sanei leh*, everybody should hate
him. Why is it שונאך *sonecha*, your enemy? It should be everybody
should hate him. So מאי שנא האי *mai shnah hai*, why, why
are we singling out you? אלא לאו *Ella lav*, it must be
כי האי גוונא *ki hai gavna*, like this type of a scenario
דחזיה ביה איהו דבר ערוה *d'hazye bei ihu dvar ervah*, you saw
him do some sexual sin, interesting why דווקא *davka* sexual, but that's
where the יצר הרע *yetzer hara* is and that's where things are
done more in private and therefore you who know it are entitled
to hate him, but other people don't because they don't know it
and you're not supposed to be telling other people. So רב נחמן
בר יצחק אמר מצוה לשנאותו *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar mitzvah lesanoso*,
it's not just you're allowed to and it's a מצוה *mitzvah* to
hate him שנאמר יראת ה' שנאי רע *shene'emar yirat Hashem sonei ra*.
So those who fear God hate evil. Now gets to the question
of do you hate
רשעים *reshaim*, do you the sin or the sinner, do you hate
evil or do you hate evil-doers and how this factors into all
these issues about אהבת ישראל *ahavat Yisrael* and the מצוה *mitzvah* to
be אוהב ohev, *ohev* and how much is a person a very
willful sinner and so on. But anyway, אמר רב אחא בריה דרבא
לרב אשי *Amar Rav Acha brei de-Rava le-Rav Ashi*, רב אחא בריה
דרבא *Rav Acha brei de-Rava* says to רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, מהו
למימרא ליה לרביה למסניה *mahu lemeimrei leh lerabbeih lemisnaye*, and this is
important question gets back to this issue about reporting abuse and so
on
but still some people have to know. Maybe you should tell this
guy's master, let's say he's a student or maybe it means his
employer, and that he should hate him even though it won't be
accepted as testimony in fact and he won't be prosecuted in the
court but people have to know how to deal with him. אמר
ליה אי ידע דמהימן לרביה כבי תרי *Amar leh iy yada de'meheiman
lerabbeih ke-bei terei*, if you know you'll be trusted to his master
like two witnesses, that your testimony will be trusted, then לימרא ליה
*leimrei leh* you should tell the master because at the end of
the day you know this guy is doing the wrong thing. So
it's not really a bad repute about him, it's a true repute
but one that will not be believed by people and will be
seen as the worst לשון הרע *Lashon Hara*. I understand, but if
you know that your report will be trusted and accepted and won't
be rejected and then it'll lead to all this questionable suspicion, then
לימרא ליה *leimrei leh* you should say ואי לא לא לימרא ליה
*ve-i lo lo leimrei leh* and it's not you shouldn't because this
is not formal testimony. This is the balance between we're not prosecuting
him in court but if I know something about this guy then
and you're going to hire him let's say or you're his רבי
*Rebbe*, you need to know something about him because we're all trying
to do good for the people he interacts with, for כלל ישראל
*Klal Yisrael*, for him himself. So I'm not talking about formal testimony,
how do you strike that balance and this is always the question,
should I share this with so-and-so? I saw something, I know something,
nobody else, report to the
police, but I'm saying even in cases, I turn this into a
discussion of abuse of innocent victims, in the גמרא *Gemara* it's really
also just question of improper behavior. I know something, I know something
about this guy, I know he's having an affair with so-and-so, two
consenting adults, should I tell X, should I tell Y? I know
something about him and he's about to be hired by this person,
I'm the only one who knows it, should I tell this about
somebody? So this is a question about you tell it, do you
wind up looking bad, does he look bad, are you believed, are
you not believed? So at the by the end the גמרא *Gemara*
says if it's going to be believed and if it's somebody who
needs to know then you should report it and I think that
it is key, yes.
The language of לשנוא *lisno* is it can't just be like in
the modern sense like a feeling in your heart. It might not
mean once you determine that you could tell the שנאה *sin'ah* means
some type of social approbation.
I think that's a good point, most of
the we don't allow them to come to שול *shul*
right, like the מצוה *mitzvah* of אהבה *ahavah* is how you act
towards somebody and
שנאה *sin'ah* might be the absence of אהבה *ahavah*, don't act to
him in these ways as opposed to just not inviting him for
exactly. No, thank you for pointing that out, yes the אהבה *ahavah*
the מצוה *mitzvah* of אהבת ישראל *ahavat Yisrael* is very much action-oriented
and שנאה *sin'ah* as well. And look, biblically I think
Sassi, the point is that I think if people have said like
in Semitic cultures the emphasis is about how you demonstrate your actions
through your feelings through your actions, not just what those feelings are.
I want to end though with reading a very important תוספות Tosfos
*Tosafot* because תוספות Tosfos. *Tosafot* says the famous גמרא *Gemara* is if
you hate somebody, if this guy is the one you hate, you
should first take care of his donkey, even the more trivial thing,
even loading the donkey up afterwards rather than unloading the donkey of
the guy you love because it's important to sort of subdue your
יצר הרע *yetzer hara* for hating this guy. תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* says
what
יצר הרע *yetzer hara* we just said. So what do you, what
do you mean you should first do him to get, to deal
with your יצר הרע of hating him? So תוספות דבור המתחיל dibur
hamatchil אוהב, very insightful תוספות. I'll just skip to the answer. He
says, or he's three lines down, I'll
read: והשתא מציאת יצר שייך כיון דמצוה לשנאו. vehashta metziat yetzer shayach
kevan demitzvah lisno. ויש לומר veyesh lomar כיון שהוא שונאו, kevan shehu
soneh o, you hate him justifiably. What's gonna happen? גם חברו שונא
אותו. gam chavero soneh oto. You hate me, I hate you right
back, right? Hatred breeds hatred. כדכתיב כמים הפנים לפנים כן לב האדם
לאדם. kedichtiv kamayim hapanim lapanim ken lev haadam laadam. The same way
water reflects your face, feelings get reflected back. So you hate him
justifiably, he's gonna hate you back, and then what's gonna happen? Then
he hates you back, then you're gonna hate him back again, having
nothing to do with the first reason why you started hating him
in the first place. ובא מתוך כך לידי שנאה גמורה ושייך כפיית
היצר. uvah mitoch kach lidei sinah gemurah veshayach kfiyat hayetzer. So a
very I think powerful תוספות about that reality. You might be justified,
but then it leads to him hating you and then you hating
him, all of that in a very unjustifiable way, and therefore you
have to really work on that hatred. So how much do you,
can you do the מצוה לשנאו? mitzvah lisno? I think is an
important question, given to, given to what it will bring. Okay.
שנאה גוררת שנאה. sinah goreret sinah. Yeah, absolutely.
Almost like a נעשה לפניו כהיתר, naaseh lefanav keheter, you know.
You're feeling one thing but acting
another. Right. It's almost against לא תשנא. lo tisnah. What's that from?
Something
about
approaching the
person... What about, I'm sorry, what?